Finding Aid for Monica Smiley Papers 1982-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Monica Smiley Papers 1982-1984
Smiley, Monica.
1 linear ft.
Officer with the Michigan Conference of the National Organization for Women. Administrative and topical files relating to her NOW activities.
85377 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Monica Smiley (donor no. 7117 ) in October 1984.
The collection is open for research.
Monica Smiley, a native of Bay City, earned a bachelor's degree in journalism from Bradley University in Peoria, Illinois. She worked as a newspaper reporter and editor, as well as a magazine and newsletter editor and publisher. Beginning in 1978, Smiley was employed by Photo Marketing Association International of Jackson where she was promoted to Director of Communications and Editor and Publisher of Photo Marketing magazine. She resigned her position at Photo Marketing Association in 1984 to assist in the establishment of impact Publishing Company of Jackson, where she serves as vice-president.
An outspoken feminist, Ms. Smiley has been active in the women's movement. She held a variety of leadership positions in the Jackson Chapter of the Michigan Conference of the National Organization for Women. From 1979 to 1981, she was president of the Jackson Chapter. At the state level she served as conference secretary, co-editor of the Michigan NOW Times, and administrative vice-president. She was elected to the presidency of the Michigan Conference of NOW in 1983.
The papers, 1982-1984, reflect Ms. Smiley's involvement with the Michigan Conference of NOW. They have been arranged into two series: Administrative Files and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Equal Rights Amendments; National Organization for Women. Michigan Conference.; Smiley, Monica.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Women's rights--Michigan.; Women social reformers--Michigan.; Social reformers--Michigan.
- Administrative files
  Administrative Files consist of bylaws, minutes, correspondence, newsletters, and press releases of the Michigan Conference. Also included are papers relating to the Education Task Force, Legislative Liaison, Political Action Committee, and the 1983 and 1984 state conferences.
  - Bylaws, 1982 and 1983 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - State Coordinating Council, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
    - State Officers Meetings, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Education Task Force, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - Leadership Lists, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Legislative Liaison, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Memos from National office, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Hotline, 1983 and undated (Box 1)
    - Local Chapters (scattered dates)
      - Ann Arbor-Washtenaw County (Box 1)
      - Battle Creek (Box 1)
      - Dearborn (Box 1)
      - Detroit (Box 1)
      - Downriver (Box 1)
      - Jackson (Box 1)
      - Macomb (Box 1)
      - Midland (Box 1)
      - Northwest Wayne County (Box 1)
      - Saginaw/Bay Area (Box 1)
      - Traverse City (Box 1)
      - Ypsilanti (Box 1)
    - Memo to Great Lakes Regional Leadership, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Political Action Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - State Conference
    - 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
- Topical files
  Topical Files contain information on matters relating to women's issues. Among these issues are ERA, and legislation regarding sexual orientation, sexual assault, and non-discriminatory insurance rates. The researcher should consult the Legislative Liaison folder in conjunction with the topical files. The folder on the 1984 U.S. presidential campaign contains papers relating to NOW's endorsement of Mondale-Ferraro as well as material distributed by the Women's Truth Squad on Reagan, and Sonia Johnson campaign literature. The last folder consists of papers relating to a 1984 seminar on valuing work held in Bay City. Included in this folder is Ms. Smiley's speech on comparable worth in the communications and media industry.
  - Dressel Amendment to Elliott-Larsen Civil Rights Act, 1983 (re Sexual Orientation) (Box 1)
  - ERA, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Sexual Assault, 1984 (Box 1)
  - U.S. Presidential Campaign, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Unisex Insurance Rates, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Valuing Work Seminar, Bay City, 1984 (Box 1)